<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A tru[e] relati[on] of the pro[cee]dings of the Bauarian and Spa[nish] forces before the city Heydelburgh hauing very strongly besiedged it. As also, the marching of the King of Bohemia and Count Mansfield, with their forces into Alsatia, belonging to Leopoldus the emperours brother, and the Duke of Brunsvvicke into Bauaria. Likewise, the newes from most of the prouinces of Europe, that therein you may behold, the afflicted estate of Christendome, with the various changes whereunto man is subiected.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.61</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850278</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850278</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08164)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 826:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A tru[e] relati[on] of the pro[cee]dings of the Bauarian and Spa[nish] forces before the city Heydelburgh hauing very strongly besiedged it. As also, the marching of the King of Bohemia and Count Mansfield, with their forces into Alsatia, belonging to Leopoldus the emperours brother, and the Duke of Brunsvvicke into Bauaria. Likewise, the newes from most of the prouinces of Europe, that therein you may behold, the afflicted estate of Christendome, with the various changes whereunto man is subiected.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19 [i.e. 21], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nicholas Bourne, and Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at the Royall Exchange, and Popeshead-Pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Now = Newsbooks 61.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1595 on UMI microfilm reel 826.</note>
                  <note>Numerous pages misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 1595.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page mutilated, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Europe --  History --  1517-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> RELATI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> OF THE PRO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dings of the Bauarian and Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> forces before the City Heydelburgh, hauing very ſtrongly beſiedged it.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO, <hi>The marching of the King of</hi> Bohemia <hi>and Count</hi> Mansfield, <hi>with their forces into</hi> Allatia, <hi>belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to</hi> Leopoldus <hi>the Emperours brother, and the Duke</hi> of Brunſwicke <hi>into</hi> Bauaria.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LIKEWISE,</hi> The newes from moſt of the Prouinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> that therein you may behold, the afflicted eſtate of Chriſtendome, with the Various Changes whereunto man is ſubiected.</p>
            <p>Printed the 11. of Iulii. <hi>Sua cuique mihi mea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Popeshead-Pallace.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:15468:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15468:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The firſt letter from Conſtantinople,</hi> the <hi>10.</hi> of Iune <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVE vnderſtand from Tartaria that there is great muſtering of men, and that they intend to challenge the Throne of <hi>Othoman,</hi> hauing heard of the death of <hi>Oſman,</hi> the great Turke: for this it ſtands, all that vaſt Countrey from Ruſſia to the Indian and Atlantick Seas, is diuided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt three chames of ancient and noble race: The firſt is called <hi>Tartar Cham,</hi> a mighty Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, poſſeſſing the Prouince Mangia beſides diuers other great Countreyes: The ſecond <hi>Tartar Mechrit,</hi> vnder whom is <hi>deſertum de lop;</hi> and many Nations to the Caſpian Sea. The third is <hi>Tartar Chrim,</hi> diſcending directly from the Family of <hi>Othoman,</hi> who both by birth and contract may challenge the Imperiall Crown of Turkey, if that line ſhall faile, as is thought that he will doe now, or otherwiſe reuenge the murther of the aforeſaid <hi>Oſman</hi> vpon the Ianniſſaries.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15468:3"/>
            <p>Alſo the Letters from <hi>Venice</hi> make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſome of the principall offenders that layed their hands on the Emperor, are fled, and that the reſt at home are diuided, ſome holding with <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and ſome with a yonger brother of <hi>Oſman</hi> aforeſaid. And that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> deſires not the <hi>Empire,</hi> longing one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to viſit the Temple of <hi>Mecha,</hi> being raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the promiſes of <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They write alſo, that the principall <hi>Muſty,</hi> and ſome Doctors of the Law, haue fore-told and preſaged the determination, and finall end of the Turkiſh greatneſſe, perſwading the Viſirs at the imitation of the Graecians, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one to ſtep in for a Kingdome, or more.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Perſia</hi> they certifie vs, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, through this diſſention in <hi>Turkey,</hi> they haue gotten good opportunity to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Tauris,</hi> and other places left; the Sophy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much diſpleaſed with the inſolent mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the great Turke (as one Prince may act anothers part) is onely reſolued to raiſe an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to be reuenged on the <hi>Ianniſſaires,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the <hi>Beglerbeg</hi> of <hi>Arabia</hi> hath ſent him a preſent of diuers braue Horſes.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15468:3"/>
            <p>From <hi>Alexandria</hi> we heare, that the plague is ſo great in <hi>Gran Cayro,</hi> that about 80000. there haue beene buried within the ſpace of foure moneths, and that the Iewes are flock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſuch numbers to the Sea Townes, whereby the traffick is much augmented, and increaſed in the Straites.</p>
            <p>From Algier they write, that the Pirate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to erect a Common wealth among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and haue written to the Hollanders, that if they will vnite with their forces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they will make an notable attempt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dominions of the King of Spaine, and begin a poſſeſſion there.</p>
            <p>It is reported here that at Naples there hath been an attempt made vpon the Viceroy by the Nobility and inhabitants, being perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a dearth: but they cry out vpon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as liberty, and lye in waite to put ſome thing in execution.</p>
            <p>Theſe that come from Rome, relate that the Pope hath giuen a free indulgence and pardon of ſinnes to all them that will ſerue the Emperour in his wars, wherupon many ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and great ſtore of money are ſent vnto him.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15468:4"/>
            <p>The Signorie of Venice hath ſent lately diuers Gallies at Sea, beſides ſome Gulleons towards Candia, and fortified the Harbours in Hiſtria and Dalmatia, and vpon the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent about Crema and Breſcia, prouideth all the places of importance with ſtrong gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons.</p>
            <p>Letters of Millane make mention, that there hath beene an inſurrection amongſt the Griſons, whereby diuers Spaniards and Imperialiſts haue beene ſlaine, and many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces forſaken, not without great terrour of the reſt.</p>
            <p>From Genoa it is certified, that ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers haue taken ſanctuary, or Aſylum, being denied a protection from Spaine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſay their debts ariſe, for being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged about the Catholike Kings affaires.</p>
            <p>They write from Florence and Luca, that there is great complaint againſt the Engliſh, ſeeing they deale not for ſo many ſilkes as they were vſed to doe; and therefore they will endeauour to make cloth and cottens of their owne, and not trade with <hi>England,</hi> as in times paſt.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15468:4"/>
            <p>From <hi>Poland</hi> the Newes is, that the Ieſuites are hatefull to the Inhabitants, wherupon the <hi>Lords</hi> of the Country haue petitioned to the Maieſtie of <hi>Sigiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to baniſh, or diſmiſſe them, about which there is great diſcontent occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and heere giue me leaue a little by way of transſition to wonder at this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, why they? ouer all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Religion ſhould ſo far vary from true Religion, as to delight in murther, combuſtion of Kingdomes, oſtentation of knowledge, rapture of viſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns, and eſpecially ſetting Princes at diviſion, yea breaking the band of amitie betweene Prince and Subiect, ſure I can yeeld you no r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſon for it? but this as it fareth with Children, who ſucking of a froward nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes breaſt become accordingly froward and pettiſh in their liues: ſo they having one <hi>Ignatius Loyalta</hi> a Souldier to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a fiery diſpoſition, no doubt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his name, doe immitate him in the fierie and bloody ſtepps of warre and diſſention: God grant that all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15468:5"/> may take heede of their pollicies. For in my Conſcience they would pull down the <hi>Papacy,</hi> if they could, and ſet vp their owne Superintendancy.</p>
            <p>They alſo write, that from the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Leopolis</hi> and the Country adiacent, much Corne hath beene tranſported to <hi>Constantin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple</hi> in this time of their dearth through the Blacke Sea, whereby they haue beene wonderfully enriched, as the Turkes neighbourly are releived.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Spaine,</hi> there is newes of the feare of the Mores, who haue lately made an attempt in <hi>Granado,</hi> and word is brought by a <hi>Brazill</hi> man into <hi>Portingall,</hi> that the wilde men about the River of <hi>Amazones,</hi> haue rebelled againſt the <hi>Portingals,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who governe the Country and rule there. Much like that vnfortunate miſchiefe which hath happened of late in Virginia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where we heare almoſt 300. of the Engliſh Plantation were ſlaine by the perfidiouſnes of the old Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, from <hi>Vienna</hi> the 22, day, This Cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie is much quieted ſince the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15468:5"/> Marriage, for heere are many Nobles and Ladies, who profeſſe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and haue their Congregations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the walles of the Cittie, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſometime of fortie or fiftie Coaches, all which liue here vndiſturbed by reaſon the Empereſſe entertaines them graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and they attend the Court with all humilitie when occaſion ſerveth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before they ſtood vppon their guard, and their Servants rodd with piſtols and petronels to the Church: And (God be thanked) the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> cannot divert him from his reſolution, to keepe good quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with his Subiects, although they haue many times attempted the ſame. Or other wiſe it may be, their great numbers keepe all in awe, and that the Emperour is loath to be troubled with warres abroad, and diſſentions at home.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Odenburgh,</hi> is here newes that the Emperour propoſed to the Lords and States, the Coronation of his Sonne, but that they abſolutely denyed it, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made choice of another.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15468:6"/>
            <p>It was alſo Reported, that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackes having no Warres in Poland, threatned to come downe into Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, which the Ieſuits vrged, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour intertayned, but it is ſayd, and thought, the Tartarians and Ruſſians will keepe them backe with their Incurſions and Enterpriſes, which they intend to make ſhortly.</p>
            <p>In thoſe parts are ſtill made great mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterings, to ſupply the Emperours warres. This Cittie, <hi>Prague</hi> it ſelfe, hath guard and watch like a Towne of warre, and they beate vnto the <hi>Parado,</hi> as if the enemie lay before it. In plaine termes, they are iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous one of another, and the Heires and Friends of thoſe whom the Emperour put to execution, long to be revenged. As for the Iewes, though they generally reioyce at thoſe diſſentions among <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> and ſlaughtering one another, yet doe they particularly rather fauour the Proteſtants then the Catholiques.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Moravia,</hi> wee vnderſtand that the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15468:6"/> Marquis of <hi>Iaggerendorf,</hi> remayneth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and hath written to Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into <hi>Bavaria,</hi> alledging if hee doe attempt that, he ſhall be ſure to finde many Friends for his paſſage into <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> where, if the warre beganne againe, no queſtion, ſome great alteration will follow: for <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> is now at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to take his part, and will queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe aſſiſt him, if he can proſecute any courſe to come neere him.</p>
            <p>The fourth, from <hi>Cullen</hi> the firſt of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The Baron of <hi>Anholt</hi> hath threatned the Countrey of the Landtgraue of <hi>Heſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> in behalfe of the Imperialiſtes; hee intends to recover the places in <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> taken by the Duke <hi>Chriſtian</hi> of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> but the Inhabitants are all rather for <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> then the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen,</hi> from whom they were taken.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Franckfort</hi> we vnderſtand, that the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> hath impoſed a harſh Commandement in his Townes, for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15468:7"/> ſearching of Paſſengers, and although he ſeemeth diſcontent at <hi>Bavaria's</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, yet doth he governe Sileſia for the Emperour, or at leaſt ſo much of it as the Catholiques are willing to ſubmit vnto him. But among other things, the Biſhops are moſt fierce againſt the Proteſtants, and will not ſuffer them to goe vnto their Churches.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Poland</hi> we haue Newes, that the inhabitants being become loath of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, the Nobilitie hath requeſted the King, either to baniſh or diſmiſſe them, about which is great diſcontent occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>They write from <hi>Noragrad</hi> in Ruſſia, that the Ieſuites had layd a plott with certaine Pruſſians, to robbe and ſurpriſe the Abbey of Saint <hi>Nuclay</hi> in <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> adioyning almoſt to the Sea, which they did either out of envie, at the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Greeke Church, then which there is nothing more hatefull to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or out of a common diſpoſition, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15468:7"/> wicked perverſeneſſe to raiſe quarrels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Countries, and nouriſh enmitie betweene Princes.</p>
            <p>The laſt from <hi>Franckfort,</hi> the firſt of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. After the arrivall of the Duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> at <hi>Mainhem,</hi> where he was ſtately well-commed; the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countrey was not able to ſuſtaine his Forces, called a Counſell of Warre, and reſolved to depart; leaving the <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate</hi> to the care and tuition of the Lord <hi>Belfaſt,</hi> and Generall <hi>Vere;</hi> with whom he alſo left eight thouſand men more then they had, and ſo they devided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they preſently marched ten thouſand horſe, and twentie thouſand Foote.</p>
            <p>The King and <hi>Mansfeild</hi> ar now in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia,</hi> proſecuting the Warre there againſt the Emperours Brother <hi>Leopaldus,</hi> burning, ſpoyling, and taking the Countrey to his obedience, the which will conſtraine <hi>Tilly</hi> ſoone to forſake the ſiege of <hi>Heidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge,</hi> and follow the King, and ſo by this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15468:8"/> meanes divert the Warre into his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Countrey: He hath ſent the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> into <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to furniſh the Kings Armie with proviſion, and then to march and ioyne both together, and ſo to goe forward as toward Bohemia, as God ſhall giue them leaue. They were no ſooner gone, but <hi>Tilly</hi> advanced his Forces towardes <hi>Ladenburgh,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Heidelburgh.</hi> Whereupon Sir <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Herbert</hi> Commaunder there of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, aſſembled the Burgers and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to know both their abilitie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, whether they would endure the ſiege or no, &amp; how long they thought their proviſion would laſt: they anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red generally, that they would liue and die with him, and ſo they prepared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to endure the ſiege. And it was thought that <hi>Tilly</hi> did this rather to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them from their Iourney into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> then to beſtow ſo much time in the ſiege of a Towne which could profit him l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle in the obtaining more, then the poſſeſſion of the place, vnleſſe the Emperour were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15468:8"/> reſolued contrary to his owne Embaſſy, to make it a continuall warre. <hi>Tilly</hi> going on with his ſiege, tooke two of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and cut off their heads, which he pitched vpon poles, turning their faces toward the towne to terrifie the Burgers: but they in requitall cut off fiue ſouldier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> heads, &amp; ſerued them ſo likewiſe. <hi>Gonſales</hi> in the meane time being at <hi>Opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nheim,</hi> was yet doubtfull whether he would ſet vpon <hi>Mainheim</hi> or <hi>Frankendale,</hi> and ſo to get the Palatinate at once, leſt it be gotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: but there is a God that holdeth the windes in his hands, and will no doubt hold backe that reſolution, which muſt be the cauſe of ſo much blood-ſhedding, if the warres ſhould goe forward in ſuch a manner: but what will be the iſſue, time will reueale.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> miſtruſting lately the forraging of his countrey by the Imperials, writ to the Princes of the vnion concerning the ſame, who all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, that their cauſe was a common feare, and therefore they would liue and die together in maintaining the generall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15468:9"/> cauſe of Religion, and particular defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one anothers Countrey.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Letter was likewiſe ſet downe the reſolution of diuers Imperiall Cities, <hi>viz. Auſpurg, Norremburg, Witten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, Francfort, Strasburg,</hi> and ſome other, for the maintaining of the confeſſion of <hi>Auſpurg,</hi> which was the reſolution of the Proteſtant Faith, bought out long ſince by great ſummes of Money of <hi>Rodolphus</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> former Emperors. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon theſe Cities fortified their walls, had their Burgers in Armes, for feare to bee ſurprized.</p>
            <p>We haue heard from <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> that the Imperials had lately gone about to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the ſaid Citie, and had gotten fortie men through a Vault within the Walls, but were all preſently ſhot to death, and the Citie preſerued of that dangerous en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Hungaria</hi> the matters ſtand yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: the <hi>Hungarians</hi> haue flatly denyed the Coronation of the Emperors ſonne: the Clergie deſires to haue all the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall goods backe againe, with the arrera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15468:9"/> but the States and Lay-men will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them but a part. They can neyther agree vpon many other points: ſo that it is likely nothing will be concluded at the Dyet.</p>
            <p>Here was flying newes, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror was taken priſoner, but it is not true: but this is certaine, <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> and the Lord <hi>Bridiani</hi> are very ſtrongly marched vp in armes.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of <hi>Glatz</hi> and <hi>Klingenburgh</hi> ſtand yet brauely out, and haue lately giuen a great Ouerthrow vnto the Imperialliſts, and they grow daily ſtronger &amp; ſtronger. The old Count of <hi>Thorne</hi> is reported to be vpon the way with 26000. men, to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue them.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Denmarke</hi> they write, that the King hath ſent diuerſe Preſents to the <hi>Queene</hi> of <hi>Bohemia</hi> at the <hi>Hage,</hi> and written ſundry Letters of comfort &amp; conſolation, aſſuring of his aſſiſtance as wel of Men as Money: and that hee hath requeſted the Hauen Townes to arme diuers Souldiers to goe into <hi>Westphalia,</hi> to helpe and ſupply thoſe garriſons which <hi>Brunſwick</hi> left there.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15468:10"/>
            <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> lately come from <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> report, that the Captaine of <hi>Calmar</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle was called in queſtion for his life, as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing betrayed by a counterfeit letter, written by ſome ſecret malitious enemy, as though the ſame came from <hi>Poland</hi> for the ſurrendring of the fort when time ſhould ſerue: but his innocency ſaued his life, and the matter was ſoone taken vp.</p>
            <p>From <hi>France</hi> it is written, that the king is reſolued to go forward in his enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Proteſtant townes. That the Ieſuites are iealous of the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and he gets but the kings diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by his violent courſes. That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants will rather make ſallies and die in the field then in their houſes. That <hi>Mountalbo</hi> is ſo well prouided of all kind of prouiſion, that they thinke the king will not eaſily b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſiege it againe. Thoſe of <hi>Mompellier</hi> prepare themſelues likewiſe, if his Maieſtie would attempt any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p>That the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> increaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h his army dayly, and hopeth vpon a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>France.</hi> That the king is much
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15468:10"/> diſcontented, and hath a growing diſeaſe vpon him. That the <hi>Rochellers</hi> take dayly prizes, and were reſolued to make a ſally vpon the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon,</hi> being ſtrong and able to miniſter many braue ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. That there is a prohibition for the landing of the Engliſh at <hi>Callice,</hi> or on thoſe Coaſts. That diuers Apologies are written in the defence of the Proteſtants, and that the Queene laboureth what ſhe may to pacifie the troubles.</p>
            <p>From <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſels</hi> they write, that if the Ambaſſadours doe not ſuddenly agree vpon a peace, it is feared that the warre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will increaſe both in the Palatinate, and the Low Countries. My Lord of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gile</hi> hath almoſt filled his Regiment, and they lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke for foure or fiue thouſand Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more to come vnto them within this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weekes.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Hag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> we heare, that the Prince of <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ang</hi> is marched vp with a braue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with reſolution to ſet downe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore <hi>Shertog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> &amp; hath ſent for all his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines out of <hi>England</hi> to attend his ſeruice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> no queſtion <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eola</hi> will follow him. Wee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15468:11"/> heare alſo, that there are publicke Faſts and ſet Prayers for the affaires of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate.</p>
            <p>They write alſo, that his ſubiects of <hi>Austria, Stiria, Curniola,</hi> and <hi>Curinthia,</hi> haue petitioned to his Maiſtie, that as they proue good and obedient ſubiects vnto him, it would pleaſe him to be a gratious Lord vnto them, to giue them leaue to liue in the libertie of their conſcience, and die in the profeſſion of the Goſpel, that liuing and dying they may giue God the praiſe for his protection, who ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the hearts of kings, and his Maieſtie the honour of their welfare, for being ſo beneficiall vnto them.</p>
            <p>Wee doe further vnderſtand, that there is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> for their further helpe in the great enterpriſes they intend, ten thouſand horſe and foote of <hi>Switzers,</hi> and ten thouſand horſe and foote of <hi>Bohemians:</hi> and that the old Earle of <hi>Thorne</hi> is gone to releeue <hi>Glatz</hi> with twentie foure thouſand horſe and foote,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15468:11"/> and that <hi>Iagenſdorpe</hi> is marching toward the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with thirty thouſand horſe and foote, and that <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> will not bee long abſent from the King: God (I hope) will rayſe vp friends to helpe his true Church, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Greatneſſe of the Enemies.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
